So,
דף קכ"א Daf Kuf Kaf Aleph 121.
We actually start at the very bottom of ק"כ Kuf Kaf and
the discussion is about liquid and whether liquids that come from solids
or liquefy solids have recognized halakhic status. And we quoted a lot
of verses where they do, about חלב Chelev and חמץ Chametz and
so on. But now we've quoted when it comes to תרומה, Terumah,
some say that they don't, only the ones that the Torah recognizes,
which are wine and oil, and not other types of liquid, let's
say that would come from grain, even something that would be biblically
תרומה. Terumah. So we're going to end up with on this sort
of qualified or perhaps, you know, negative note in terms of the
status of liquids. Let's take a look.
והדתנן, Ve-ha-detnan, it is eight lines from the bottom.
והדתנן, Ve-ha-detnan, that which we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, אין מביאין
בכורים משקה אלא היוצא מן הזיתים ומן הענבים, Ein mevi'in bikkurim mashkeh
ela hayotzei min hazeisim umin ha'anavim,
that you can only bring בכורים Bikkurim if it's—now remember we said
before you have to initially designate it as fruit, but afterwards it
said that if you turned it into liquid, it's acceptable. But here
it's saying the only liquid that you can bring is olives and—what
comes out of olives and grapes, meaning olives and—excuse me, olives and
grapes, meaning oil and wine. So מני, Manni, who is this going
like? רבי יהושע היא, Rabbi Yehoshua hi, it's רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
that also said by תרומה Terumah that anything that's not—that's not wine
and olive oil doesn't have any status. אמר דמי ליה וקבע לה,
Amar dami leh ve-kava lah, he says by תרומה Terumah you learn
out from בכורים Bikkurim but you put it in the context of
תרומה, Terumah, and תרומה Terumah the Torah explicitly mentions wine and oil.
וגמר לה לבכורים מתרומה, Ve-gamar lah le-bikkurim mi-terumah, and then you—and then
once you say that by תרומה, Terumah, you go back and you
apply it back to בכורים. Bikkurim. וגמר לה לבכורים מתרומה, Ve-gamar lah
le-bikkurim mi-terumah, and then you learn בכורים Bikkurim back from תרומה. Terumah.
That—the same way תרומה Terumah is only wine and oil, so בכורים
Bikkurim also only wine and oil, those are the only recognized liquids.
והדתנן, Ve-ha-detnan, that which we taught in our משנה, Mishnah, אין סופגים
את הארבעים משום ערלה אלא היוצא מן הזיתים ומן הענבים. Ein sofgin
es ha-arba'ah mishum orlah ela hayotzei min hazeisim umin ha'anavim. So before—so
now we're saying that even ערלה Orlah is something that you are—is
only going to apply
to—you'll only get lashes for ערלה, Orlah, right, the unripe fruit—not unripe,
first three years of the fruit, if it's—if you drink the liquid
form of it, only if you drink olive oil or wine or
grape juice presumably, but nothing else, no other liquid form. מני, Manni,
who is this going like? The גמרא Gemara says רבי יהושע היא,
Rabbi Yehoshua hi, the same רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua דאמר דמי ליה
וקבע לה, de-amar dami leh ve-kava lah, so you apply first in
the context of תרומה, Terumah, in תרומה Terumah the Torah only mentions
wine and oil. וגמר לה לבכורים מתרומה, Ve-gamar lah le-bikkurim mi-terumah, and
we just said that then you go back and apply that to
בכורים, Bikkurim, so בכורים Bikkurim would only be wine and oil.
והדר מייתי לה לערלה פרי פרי מבכורים, Ve-hadar maiti lah le-orlah pri
pri mi-bikkurim, and then you have a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah of
פרי, pri, it says by בכורים, Bikkurim, פרי האדמה, pri ha-adamah, and
the פרי pri by the ערלה, Orlah, and therefore you say—and therefore
you say that the same way בכורים Bikkurim is only wine and
oil, ערלה Orlah is also only wine and oil. So after a
whole דף daf where we said, oh, everything in liquefied form you're
חייב chayav for and so on, all these פסוקים, pesukim, in the
end we say by תרומה, Terumah, בכורים, Bikkurim, and ערלה, Orlah, at
least there's a position that says no, only wine and oil. Now
even that position seems to be a limited handful number of things
that are excluded from the general rule. The problem is, or the
other factor to consider, is that the גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim
actually quotes this הלכה halakhah that you don't get lashes for ערלה
Orlah unless it's wine and oil, and says from here we understand
that—or first tries to prove one thing from it and in the
end he concludes that that's because any juice of fruits that's not
wine and oil is considered זיעה בעלמא, zei'ah be'alma, just mere sweat,
like has no halakhic status at all. And that's a very big
global statement that seems to say that the general rule is that
actually the water that comes from fruit has no halakhic status. And
I should say largely in הלכה halakhah that's how we treat the
fruit juices. Meaning, for example, by שבת, Shabbos, the only type—you're not
allowed to squeeze any fruit or almost any fruit on שבת, Shabbos,
but the only one that you actually violate שבת Shabbos דאורייתא de-oraita
for is squeezing oil, olives and grapes, because only that is recognized
as really producing something sort of meaningful as a result. And in
many, many הלכות, halakhos, anything that is not olive oil or wine
or grape juice, even grape juice there was—was young wine because it
was not—they didn't boil it so it could eventually ferment. Anyway, anything
that was not that was basically didn't have—barely any halakhic status. Can
you take תרומות ומעשרות terumos u-ma'asros from a fruit after it's been
squeezed?
Very doubtful, very questionable. So at least when it comes to fruit
juices, which is by the way the last three cases here were
all fruit juices as opposed to like liquefying your meat, there the
general rule is that things that are liquid forms don't count, only
the fruit counts.
And so—and that raises a general question about what is the general
rule and what's the exception. Is the general rule that a liquid
form is not significant about something unless—you know, and maybe we have
a few exceptions about חלב. Chelev. and חמץ *chametz* etc., or is
the general rule that it is, except or maybe the general rule
is that by fruit juices, only wine and oil, nothing else, but
maybe liquefied meat would be like a different story. This again was
at a time when nobody had ever heard about drinking orange juice
as a normal thing. I mean nobody even drank milk as a
normal thing, that's why when the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* talks about meat
and milk it always talks about cheese. So for that time, in
that sort of, in that context, the idea of juices from fruits
was crazy. But anyway, that certainly raises that important question and I
should say תוספות *Tosafot* throws in a third question as he often
does in פסחים *Pesachim*, he says, I don't get the whole thing,
תוספות *Tosafot* says, whatever happened to טעם כעיקר *ta'am k'ikar*? Whatever happened
to the taste of something counts like the thing itself? So if
I boil water with my ערלה *orlah* orange, then I'll say the
טעם *ta'am* of the orange goes into the water and makes the
water forbidden because of טעם כעיקר *ta'am k'ikar*, so why wouldn't I
squeeze out the orange juice from it, isn't it also forbidden because
of טעם כעיקר *ta'am k'ikar*? Even if you don't call it orange,
but it's something that has taste of orange in it. Now, it
could be the answer is yes, it is forbidden, but it's not
as you don't get lashes, it's not as forbidden as the original.
The primary question here is whether the thing is actually considered to
be like the original thing itself. But there are a lot of
big question marks. Is the general rule that liquid is like the
thing or not like the thing? Maybe by fruit it's, fruit certainly
it seems like we focus on wine and and olive oil. And
then the other question is even if it's not like the thing,
maybe it's still forbidden because of טעם כעיקר *ta'am k'ikar*, even if
it's not as severe as the thing itself. The final question to
mention is, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* basically conflated the cases of liquefying
something and liquids that run off of something, but logically you could
distinguish between those, maybe they should be distinguished. And the biggest, I
would say one of the biggest practical question applications of this is
the status of liquor for פסח *Pesach*. Because that is basically a
liquid that derives
from grain, through its I mean obviously and some say oh that's
like חמץ גמור *chametz gamur*, it's like here we say, if you
liquefy something or liquids that relate it's like the thing itself. Others
say, call call on the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in פסחים *Pesachim*, זיעה
בעלמא *zei'ah b'alma*, maybe it's actually permissible to drink liquor on פסח
*Pesach* even if it comes from grain, it's only זיעה *zei'ah*, it
has no status. And then there's the third possibility, well, it's not
the thing itself, it's not זיעה *zei'ah*, it's what תוספות *Tosafot* says,
טעם כעיקר *ta'am k'ikar*, at least it has the taste in it
and that at least should make it forbidden even if it's not
at the same level of severity. So the end answer here remains
very unclear, a lot of different possibilities without a clear sort of
systematization of them and clarification of them. So with that we end
our discussion of liquids and now we turn to the remainder of
the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, which talks about a few more things that
combine not to count as נבילה neveila *neveilah*, but combine to be
count as part of the food in order for it to become
טמא tamei *tamei* as foodstuff. So let's take a look. והאלל *ve'ha'alaw*,
the אלל Alal. *alaw*. So my אלל *alaw*, what is this אלל
*alaw*? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אמר amar מרתקא *Rabbi Yochanan amar martka*.
Now what's מרתקא *martka*? רש"י *Rashi* says מרתקא *martka* is this like
I guess muscle, calls it a גיד *gid*, but I assume he
means a muscle, that sort of runs down the back and up
to the side of the neck, a big thick like muscle here.
So I don't know, doctors in the room. All right, anyway, so
that's what he says, which is something that's very hard to eat.
תוספות *Tosafot* says that but presumably if you had it with meat,
you would maybe I don't know cook it together and you'd somehow
would eat it together with the meat. תוספות *Tosafot* quotes the רבנו
חננאל *Rabbeinu Chananel* who says that it's like a piece of rotting
flesh, which you would never eat by itself, but maybe if a
little part of your steak was rotting, once it's there you'll eat
it anyway, somehow you'll eat it together. Something that would not be
food by itself but would be eaten together with the rest of
the meat. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish אמר amar בשר שפלטו סכין *Resh
Lakish amar basar she'paltu sakin*, the meat that is that is sort
of spit out by the knife, which is when you're flaying an
animal and you're removing like you know how when you like peel
a cucumber, especially if you use a knife and you're not using
a peeler, like some of the actual meat of the cucumber gets
stuck to the peel. So the same is true when you're flaying
an animal, some of the meat gets stuck to the skin. So
that is meat that you normally wouldn't eat. So normally it doesn't
have a status of food, I mean it's still meat, but it's
just you throw it out, it's stuck to the skin. But because
now but presumably if you're going to eat it together the there
might be scenarios where you eat it together with the rest of
the meat, so it can count with the meat but it won't
count by itself. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will analyze that. Let's take
a look. מיתיבי meitivei. *meitivei*, I'll ask you about this, ואולם *ve'ulam*,
this is in the איוב *Iyov* complaining about his quote unquote friends
who were trying to help him understand why he was suffering so
much, ואולם אתם טפלי שקר רפאי אלל כלכם *ve'ulam atem toflei sheker
rof'ei elil kulchem*. You are all sort of plasterers of lies, healers
of an אלל *aliel* are you all. So here's the word אלל
*aliel* which we assume is the same as אלל *alaw*, which means
you're trying to heal something that can't be healed, you're trying to
heal my wounds and it's and they're not they can't be healed.
So what is this אלל *aliel*? It's something obviously that cannot be
healed. So בשלמא למאן דאמר מרתקא *bishlama leman d'amar martka*, it's this
מרתקא *martka*, היינו דלאו בר רפואה היא *hainu delav bar refuah hi*,
it can't be healed, either according to תוספות *Tosafot* it's rotting flesh,
can't be healed, or according to רש"י *Rashi* once that muscle is
severed, it can't be healed. אלא למאן דאמר בשר שפלטו סכין *ella
leman d'amar basar she'paltu sakin*, if it's some flesh that got was
spit out by the knife and got stuck to the skin, בר
רפואה היא *bar refuah hi*, if a little flesh is cut away
from a
person, then it could heal sometimes. So So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says בעלו דקרא *ba'alu dikra*, the verse, the word עלו *alu* in
the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*, דכולי עלמא לא פליגי *dekuly alma lo peligi*,
nobody debates that it's referring to this other thing, either the rotting
flesh or this muscle. כי פליגי באלו דמתניתין *Ki pligi ba'alu dematnitin*,
we want to know what the word refers to in the משנה
Mishnah. *Mishnah*, because the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* does not always use the
same language as the פסוקים *psukim*. Okay, תא שמע *ta shema*, let's
try from another משנה Mishnah
*Mishnah*. I'm at the end of our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. רבי יהודה
אומר omer *Rabbi Yehuda omer*, האלו המכונס *ha'alu hamechunas*, אם יש בו
כזית kezayis במקום אחד *im yesh bo kezayit bemakom echad*, חייב עליו
*chayav alav*. If you gather up this אלו *alu* into one place
and it's a כזית kezayis *kezayit*, then you would transgress. Presumably it
means that if it would have the טומאה tumah. *tumah* of a
נבילה neveilah. *neveilah*, and if you would touch it and let's say
eat a קרבן *korban* or enter into the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*,
you would transgress. So this אלו *alu* not only combines with meat
to be food, but it actually can be considered the נבילה neveilah.
*neveilah* itself if you gather enough of it up together in one
place. So what should that be the case? אם יש בו כזית
kezayis *Im yesh bo kezayit*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ואמר רב
הונא *ve'amar Rav Huna*, והוא שכינסו *vehu shekinso*, you have to gather
it. It's not that it got gathered by itself, meaning you intentionally
gathered it, which gives it significance, which shows that you care about
it and are intending to like eat it or, you know, so
therefore it gives it significance. בשלמא למאן דאמר בשר שפלטתו סכין *Bishlama
leman de'amar basar shepaltato sakin*, if it means meat that got stuck
to the skin, היינו דכי כנסו כזית chezayit מחייב *hainu dechi kinso
kezayit mechayev*, that makes sense, because then if you scrape it off
from the skin and you pull it all together, now you're actually
saying I'm not throwing it out, even though it got stuck to
the skin, I'm going to scrape it off and now I'm treating
it as real meat, and if you're treating it as real meat,
then it would be like a נבילה neveilah, *neveilah* and then it
would cause טומאה tumah *tumah*. So that makes sense. אלא למאן דאמר
מרתקא *Ela leman de'amar martka*, but if you say it's this מרתקא
*martka*, rotting flesh or inedible muscle, כי כזית kezayis מה הוי *ki
kezayit mah havi*, who cares if it's a כזית kezayis *kezayit*? עץ
בעלמא הוא Etz b'alma hu, *Etz be'alma hu*, it's like a piece
of wood, which fits better with Rashi's idea that it's a muscle,
you know. So anyway, who cares if you have a lot together?
It's still inedible and it still can't be considered meat. So how
can you give it the טומאה tumah *tumah* of a נבילה neveilah
*neveilah*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אליבא דרבי יהודה לא פליגי
*Aliba deRabbi Yehuda lo peligi*. You're right. According to רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* that says if you have it all together, it's a נבילה
neveilah. *neveilah*, it has to be that at least for him, this
אלו *alu* idea is referring to
the meat on the skin. Because there you can understand that when
you gather it together, you're showing you're not throwing it out, it
gives it significance. I should say parenthetically that we've been talking in
this משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* about the טומאה tumah *tumah*, the טומאה tumah,
*tumah* of a נבילה neveilah *neveilah*, food to become טמא tamei *tamei*.
And here the question is if you're planning on throwing it out,
planning on eating it, right? The meat that's on the skin, other
things like the muscle, the rotting flesh, those things are objectively not
edible. But meat that's on the skin is objectively edible, you just
normally would throw it out. So here it's your subjective intention which
is going to define its status. תוספות *Tosafot* goes out of his
way to say that cannot define its status, get it out of
the category of forbidden food. If this meat is נבילה neveilah. *neveilah*
and you're just planning on throwing it out because it's attached to
the skin, it doesn't stop it from being forbidden and from being
נבילה neveilah? *neveilah*. The idea that your intention can change the status
is in terms of טומאה tumah *tumah*. In טומאה tumah. *tumah* we
know your intention matters. Are you planning on eating something, not planning
on eating it? Do you treat it as food, not treat it
as food? So תוספות *Tosafot* goes out of his way to say
that the whole discussion here is with respect to טומאה tumah, *tumah*.
So normally this flesh on the skin you would normally throw it
out and therefore it wouldn't have the טומאה tumah, *tumah* of a
נבילה neveilah *neveilah*. But רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* would say or even
the, but then רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* would say if you gather
and scrape it off and gather it together, it's showing that you're
treating it as significant and you're planning on eating it or whatever,
then it is significant and then it has even the טומאה tumah.
*tumah* of a נבילה *neveilah*. So that clearly makes sense and it
makes sense when we're talking about the flesh that's on
the skin.
The stuff we eat is muscle. What do you mean? Like muscle
is part of the meat that we eat?
Meat we eat is muscle.
That's the part of the body we eat. Things like מרתקא *martka*,
he says ligament.
Ligament. I know רש"י *Rashi* said it was a גיד *gid*, which
literally is a ligament. But I couldn't find
what thick ligament do we have a ligament here that runs through
the neck?
There is in cows, they hold up the head.
Really? Are you sure it's not a muscle? I mean a ligament,
רש"י *Rashi* says it goes down the back, up the back and
through the neck.
Well, it could be. A ligament?
Ligamentum nuchae.
Okay. There you go. Alright, anyway. We really, when you have a
steak, that's muscle?
That's what you're eating.
You're eating the muscle. Well, so what's the meat?
Think of a chicken leg. You have the two muscles on the
chicken leg, that's what you eat on a drumstick. You're eating the
muscles. That's all you're eating.
So what's flesh though?
Flesh is also muscle. Flesh is an indescriptive, I don't think it's
a very exact term.
You mean if you peel away skin, underneath you just have muscle.
You wouldn't call that meat, you'd call that muscle, what's right underneath
the skin. That's interesting. Okay, it's interesting. Been a while since I've
taken biology. Alright, so there you go. It's a ligament then. Yes.
Next time you have a drumstick, look at it. Alright, I hear
your point. I hear your point. Okay, I hear the point.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says they forgot the meaning of this
word as in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* and רב הונא *Rav Huna*
seems to know what it is.
Right. So well, that's an interesting question. Yeah, you're right, that that
often happens. I would say it's actually an interesting point. It also
happens, you know, very often the... I... there's no ירושלמי Yerushalmi on
קדשים, Kodashim, but often the ירושלמי takes more for granted what certain
words mean than the בבלי Bavli because בבלי Bavli is dealing with
not only a passage of time but also a geographical
shift, right? And רש״י Rashi is commenting on רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda,
but right, presumably he knew what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda must mean
if he's commenting on him. Yeah, it's a good point though the
גמרא Gemara does sometimes not know what certain words mean. Yeah. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so clearly that's what רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda means. So the debate is כי פליגי רבנן, Ki pligi
Rabbanan, when the rabbis say
that it does not count by itself but it'll only count combined
with the meat, so they're certainly talking once רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
is talking about the meat left on the skin, they're certainly also
talking about that. But the question is in addition to the meat
left on the skin, are they also making this claim about this
hard ligament or this rotting flesh, depending on your position? So רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אמר amar מרתיקא נמי מצטרף, Martika nami mitztaref, he
wants to claim that according to the rabbis who say it combines,
not only this flesh on the skin combines, but even this מרתיקא
Martika combines. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish אמר דוקא בשר שפלטתו סכין, davka
basar she-paltoso sakin,
only, no, the flesh that's on the skin, that might combine. אבל
מרתיקא לא מצטרף, Aval martika lo mitztareif, but not this מרתיקא, Martika,
that is stuff you would never eat with the meat. So the
goal here is to define something that's not food itself, but you
would eat together with food, and that's what רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan
and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish are debating: would that apply even to
this ligament of the neck? Okay, but clearly we are minimally talking
about the flesh that is on the skin, and now we're going
to shift our focus to that part of it, the flesh on
the skin. So let's take a look. האי בשר שפלטתו סכין היכי
דמי? Hai basar she-paltoso sakin hechi dami? What is this case about
the flesh that's left on the skin after flaying? אי דחשיב ליה,
Iy de-chashiv leh,
if you're planning on eating it, you know, אפילו בפני עצמו מטמא,
afilu bifnei atzmo mitamei, then it's meat, then it even
will become טמא by itself because it's food, it's meat, and maybe
it's like even like the נבילה and it will cause טומאה. tuma.
ואי דלא חשיב ליה, Ve-iy de-lo chashiv leh, and if you're saying,
'Ach, I'm going to throw it out. It's stuck on the skin,
the leather,' so then בטולי בטליה, bitulei batlei, you've negated it and
it won't, and therefore why would it combine with the meat that
you are planning on eating? If you have right next to on
the plate a piece of meat you're going to eat and a
little of this meat that's on the skin that you're going to
throw out because it's connected to the leather, so why just because
טומאה tuma touches it, why would it combine to be considered a
larger amount of food? You're planning on throwing it out. So make
up your mind and if you're not going to throw it out
then it should work by itself. So the גמרא's Gemara answers here
are, you know, are היכי תמצא's, hachai timtza are like constructed cases
to answer it. Let's take a look. רב אבין ורב מיישא, Rav
Avin ve-Rav Maisha, so they both have two
explanations. חד אמר Chad amar מקצתו חישב עליו, miktzato chishav alav, that
the case is what you have here is that you are planning
on eating... you have, let's say a כזית worth of this meat
that's left on the skin in various places, right, you tried flaying
and various places combined it's a כזית worth of meat or a
כביצה kebetzah worth of meat. Okay, but you're saying in your mind,
'I'm going to take some of that meat off.' Not all of
it, some of that meat I want to scrape off. So since
it's only some, if טומאה tuma was to touch the meat there
wouldn't be a כזית worth that you're giving significance to because you're
only planning on scraping some of it off. But if you combine
that and you sit it next to meat that you are going
to eat, so then even if only some of it you're planning
on eating, if that little some tips the scale, so now you
get up to a כביצה, kebetzah, you can combine it. Which basically
at the bottom line all that means is that if you're planning
on eating it it's like food, if you're not planning on eating
it it's not food, and it's a היכי תמצא hachai timtza where
you're planning on eating some but not all,
so it's not enough to give this enough status, but because it's
only some of it you can combine with the food you're eating.
But in terms of the principle, the principle is it's either all
or nothing. If you're going to eat it it's food, if you're
not going to eat it it's not food. Okay, that's what he
says. וחד אמר, Ve-chad amar, and the other one says, where am
I, וחד אמר מקצתו פלטתו חיה מקצתו פלטתו סכין. Ve-chad amar miktzato
paltoso chaya miktzato paltoso sakin. A similar type of a scenario that
an animal tore into a cow, let's say didn't make it a
טריפה, treifa, and some of the skin now the flesh is hanging
off of the skin. And then you killed it and flayed it
and now in another place some flesh is hanging onto the skin.
You got confused which is which, which was the one that the
animal ripped, which is the one that was scraped off by you.
Somehow when the animal did it, since you would have naturally, I
don't know why, more naturally eaten that meat but the meat that
got scraped off by you you would naturally not have eaten, if
anything you would think the opposite, right? That the one that the
animal maybe has tetanus or other types of things, anyway, so therefore
again it's a case where you don't know which is which. So
therefore if it was by itself they wouldn't combine because there's not
enough, only one of the two pieces you're planning on eating. But
when it's together with other food you only need a little bit
extra to get it to the right size, so that's enough because
even if you only have one of the two pieces it's enough
to get it to the right size. In the end the principle
is the same. If you plan on eating it it's food, if
you don't. between an eating and not food, why the משנה Mishnah,
set it up so that you only combine with other stuff but
not by itself has to be some היכי תימצא. heichi timtza. That's
according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that it's talking about that part
of that type of meat. Okay. היכי תימצא Heichi timtza is like
a—it's a good question what the English translation for that is, but
it is a—it's a constructed scenario in order to explain a case.
So it's as opposed to sort of saying that the case reveals
a principle, we're going to have the case apply only to a
very specific constructed scenario. It's a way basically of bracketing a case
and not having it as, you know, sort of be larger, more
globally significant. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
so now we're done with this אלל. Now we move on to
another few cases. תנן התם, Tnan hatam, we taught over there in
טהרות, Taharos, החרטום והצפורנים Hachartom vehacipornayim by a bird, the beak and
the fingers, the claws, מטמאין ומטמאין ומצטרפין. mitammim umitammim umitztarpin. They transmit
טומאה tuma back and forth and they combine
to the minimum amount, which means that they basically either are something
that you would eat—who's going to eat a beak and claws?—or they're
serving as a שומר. shomer. It's not exactly clear, but both something
that becomes food that you will eat combines with something else adds
to the minimum size and a שומר shomer adds to the minimum
size. Those are the two principles we learned from our משנה. Mishnah
Two ways you can add to the minimum size by being a
שומר shomer or by being food that something you'll eat together with
the food. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says about this.
So the
גמרא Gemara says חרטום, chartom, the beak, עץ בעלמא הוא, that's like
wood! Who's going to eat that? And presumably it takes it for
granted that it's not doing a job of protecting any part of
the chicken. So אמר רבי אלעזר Amar Rabbi Elazar בחרטום תחתון, Bechartom
tachton, the lower beak. So the גמרא Gemara says
תחתון נמי עץ בעלמא הוא, Tachton nami etz b'alma hu, that's also
be the wood, who's going to eat the lower beak? So the
גמרא Gemara says, so תחתון של עליון, Tachton shel elyon, no, no,
I mean the palate, the underside of the top beak. So the
palate of the top beak, presumably that's edible is what the גמרא
Gemara is saying. And since it's edible you might not eat it
on its own, but if you're anyway eating the head of the
chicken you'll scrape it off and eat it together with it, so
combined with the chicken it is considered food. And therefore it gives
you the minimum
size. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, I already did it. So
אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, צפורנים, Cipornayim, now what are the
fingers, the claws, which by the way I think was also a
case in our משנה, mishna or maybe not because our משנה mishna.
was talking about a בהמה. behemah. In our משנה mishna it mentioned
the hooves. Yeah, so here we're talking about the claws. So אמר
רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, מקום המובלעין בבשר, Mekom hamuvla'in babasar, where
the fingernails are swallowed up like, you know, embedded into the skin.
So if they're underneath the skin, now again, so therefore what, will
you eat them in that case? If they're maybe you will, maybe
if they're embedded in the skin you'll eat them, maybe they're softer
there. It's hard to imagine that they're doing a job of being
a שומר shomer underneath the skin. So presumably he means you'll eat
it together with.
Really? Claws in the whole...
Ah,
that's interesting. So...
right, so that's sort of like the גמרא Gemara before mentions spices,
things that you eat together with other stuff but not by itself.
So there that's a good example. So now the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, and now קרנים, karnayim, horns. This is going back quoting our
משנה, mishna. it wasn't—chickens don't have horns. So what's the case of
horns in our משנה mishna that they count together with the meat?
אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, במקום שחותכין ויוצא מהם דם. Bemakom
shechotchin veyotzei mehem dam. Again, similar to the fingernails, where the horns
are connected to the head, so there still is blood vessels going
through it, and if you would cut, blood would run out. Now
what does that mean? Does that mean you would eat—again, there's only
two ways you can count together, either you would eat it together—hard
to imagine you would eat horns even if they're that close to
the head—if they were very poor...
right... and you're going to try to get as much meat as
possible and if there's a little bit of meat they're going to
have...
maybe you would, so there it could very well be. Or it
could be because there is blood vessels, there's also marrow, and it's
a שומר shomer to the marrow. So something that's a שומר shomer
also counts together with the meat minimum size. So with that we
end our discussion of, for now at least, of שומר shomer and
אוכל, ochel, you know, and
יד, yad, and ways in which you communicate טומאה, tuma. you add
to the minimum size of טומאה tuma? either by being a שומר
shomer or protective shell or by being something that even if it
isn't food by itself is eaten together with food. And now we
turn to the second part of the משנה, Mishnah which is a—I
think for us a little bit more of an interesting case, which
talks about a Jew ששחט הבהמה sheshachat habehemah for a non-Jew, or
a non-kosher בהמה. behemah. A Jew שחט shechats a pig for a
non-Jew, and therefore it has a middle status. From a non-Jew's perspective,
שחיטה shechitah doesn't matter, so the animal only stops being, becomes permissible,
not אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, when it dies. From a
Jew, שחיטה shechitah does everything, and from the moment you שחט shechat
it, it's not a נבלה neveilah because you שחט shechated it and
it's permissible to eat. But the משנה Mishnah is looking for a
middle scenario where שחיטה shechitah is significant enough but it's not fully
significant. Well, how would that be? For a Jew it does everything,
for a non-Jew it does nothing. So the way we get... A
middle case is when you mix the genres. So we're going to
talk about two cases. Our משנה Mishnah? is a Jew שחט shechting
a non-כשר kosher animal, a pig, for a non-Jew. So because it's
a Jew doing the act of שחיטה shechita that gives it some
significance, but because it's a pig for a non-Jew, it's not fully
significant, obviously. So that means that at the moment of שחיטה, shechita,
because שחיטה shechita would work for כשר kosher animals for Jews, it's
considered food, but it's not yet considered edible by the non-Jew because
it hasn't died. So that also means because it hasn't died that
even though when it dies it will be a נבלה, neveilah, because
even when you שחט shecht the pig it's still a נבלה, neveilah,
right, because at the end of the day, right, only כשר kosher
שחט shechted animals are not נבלה. neveilah. So it's not going to
be a נבלה neveilah until it dies. So it's in this middle
status: it's food, but it's not yet, it's not a נבלה. neveilah.
And that parallels the first case in the משנה. mishna, Be alone,
along, you שחט shechted it and it's still thrashing around, it hasn't
actually like stopped moving, fully expired. The other reverse case is as
we're going to see is a non-Jew שחט shechts an animal for
a Jew. So in that type of case, כשר kosher animal I
think, חס ושלום chas veshalom anyway, so in that type of a
case because it's a כשר kosher animal for a Jew with a
שחיטה shechita it has some significance, but because it's a non-Jew doing
it and it's not really a כשר שחיטה, kosher shechita, it's not
fully significant. So in that case as well we will say it
is a, we'll say that it, you know, it is in this
middle status that it's food but not yet a נבלה neveilah until
it dies. Okay, so we're looking for those middle cases. Normally it's
all or nothing. Again, for a non-Jew, it's not edible until it
dies and it's not a נבלה neveilah until it dies, and non-Jews,
it's almost, it's not relevant to them this נבלה. neveilah. But for
a non-כשר kosher animal, you know,
animals are נבלה, neveilah, animals for Jews are either נבלה neveilah when
they're dead or never be a נבלה neveilah because it was שחט.
shechted. Okay? Anyway, so for a non-Jew it's not relevant until it
dies and for a Jew שחיטה shechita does everything, but because there's
a Jew doing a שחיטה shechita for a non-כשר kosher animal for
a non-Jew, the שחיטה shechita makes it enough like food, but we're
still not going to call it a נבלה neveilah until it actually
dies.
If a non-Jew does שחיטה shechita properly of a כשר? kosher?
Not כשר, kosher, it's a נבלה. neveilah. That's what we learned at
the beginning of the מסכת. masechet. Yes, but that it requires the
act of a Jew. We learned way at the beginning that a
שחיטה shechita can only be done through. Well, you know, the גמרא
gemara never sort of exactly quoted a פסוק, pasuk the ראש Rosh
quotes a פסוק pasuk, I think וזבחת ואכלת ve-zavachta ve-achalta that you
know, somebody that מצאת זו, matzat zo, I forget exactly, but it's
basically learned from, you know, there's an assumption that some types of
things are only כשר kosher if done by people that are in
that halakhic category. For example, you can only,
a ספר תורה Sefer Torah written by a non-Jew, a גט get
written by a non-Jew, there are some things that require somebody to
be in that halakhic category to do the correct, to do the
right ritual act. There are some things not. There's a debate whether
מילה mila can be done by a non-Jew. There's more of a
possibility that a non-Jew could do מילה mila than a non-Jew could
do שחיטה, shechita, which is a little ironic. Okay, but basically the
point is that when we have a formal ritual act in which
procedure matters, not just end result, we often demand that the people
doing it are the people who are relevant to that category. Okay,
so let's take a look. So אמר רבי אסי, Amar Rabbi Assi,
שונים ושונים, Shonin u-shonim, we teach the following way: ישראל בטומאה ועובד
כוכבים בטהרה צריכים מחשבה. Yisrael betum'ah ve-oveid kochavim betaharah, tzrichim machshavah.
So that's exactly what I said. If a Jew שחט shechts a
non-כשר kosher animal or a non-Jew שחט shechts a כשר kosher animal,
that gives us these middle scenarios that since there was an act
of שחיטה shechita it's considered food even though it's eventually going to
be a נבלה, neveilah, because it was done by the wrong either
done on the wrong animal, a pig, or done by the wrong
person, a non-Jew. So eventually when the animal dies it'll be a
נבלה, neveilah, but since it's somewhat a relevant שחיטה shechita here, done
by a Jew, done for a כשר kosher animal, oh, or done
on a כשר kosher animal, at this stage it will be considered
food even before it has died. So they require מחשבה, machshavah, intention
to actually eat it if we're going to be considering it food,
והכשר מים ממקום אחר, ve-hekhsher mayim mimakom acher, and it needs the
water, right, all food needs water to make it considered הוכשר, huchshar,
susceptible. Now normally we say if you שחט shecht something it doesn't
need הכשר. hekhsher. You might remember from way back in the מסכת,
masechet, if Michael was here he would remind us, that the act
of שחיטה shechita actually and the, not the blood of שחיטה, shechita,
but the act of שחיטה shechita is a substitute for הכשר. hekhsher.
But that is a fully legitimate act of שחיטה. shechita. Remember, this
is not. It's either שחיטה shechita done by a non-Jew or שחיטה
shechita done to a non-כשר kosher animal. So it's, we're not going
to say it's a substitute for הכשר, hekhsher, but again because you
have some semblance of a שחיטה shechita here, it will be enough
to make it food and make it susceptible if it comes in
contact with water. הכשר למה לי? Hekhsher lama li? Why do you
need הכשר? hekhsher? Forget the שחיטה. shechita. סופו לטמא טומאה חמורה. Sofo
letamei tumah chamurah. In the end it's going to be a נבלה
neveilah because it's a pig or because it's שחט shechted by a
non-Jew. Eventually when it dies it'll be a נבלה, neveilah, it'll be
a source of טומאה. tuma. וכל שסופו לטמא טומאה חמורה, Ve-kol she-sofo
letamei tumah chamurah, anything that in the end is going to have
a weighty טומאה, tuma? being a source of טומאה, tuma לא בעי
הכשר, lo ba'i hekhsher, does not require הכשר hekhsher even if it's
at an interim stage where it is only food and it is
not yet a source of טומאה. tuma How do I know this?
דתני דבי רבי ישמעאל De-tanei devei Rabbi Ishmael we taught, וכי יותן
מים על זרע, Ve-khi yutan mayim al zera, when water comes on
seeds, that's where we learn this. of liquid making something susceptible. מה
זרעים שאין סופן לטמא טומאה חמורה צריכין הכשר, mah zraim she'ein sofan
letamei tuma chamura tzrichin hechsher,
only something like seeds that can never be the source of טומאה.
tuma Only those require הכשר, hechsher, contact with liquid. אף כל שאין
סופו לטמא טומאה חמורה צריך הכשר. af kol she'ein sofo letamei tuma
chamura tzarich hechsher. That's the general rule, only things that won't in
the end be a source of טומאה tuma, צריך הכשר. tzarich hechsher.
And what's an example of this? דתניא אמר רבי יוסי מפני מה
אמרו נבלת עוף טהור. detanya amar Rebbe Yossi mipnei mah amru nivlat
of tahor. Remember this, the carcass of a dead bird only causes
טומאה tuma. when you actually swallow it. So צריכה מחשבה ואינה צריכה
הכשר. tzricha machshava ve'eina tzricha hechsher. Now
let's say
you are actually going
to—one minute—you need to intend to eat it, so it's only going
to cause טומאה tuma, when you actually swallow it. In this state,
right, just sitting here and touching it, it doesn't cause טומאה. tumah
Okay, but—so it—but can it be considered food in order that it
could receive טומאה? tumah So he says you need צריכה מחשבה, tzricha
machshava, you need to intend to eat it to give it a
status of food, this dead bird. Okay, but you don't—it doesn't need
הכשר, hechsher, it doesn't need to come in contact with liquid. Why
not? מפני שסופו לטמא טומאה חמורה, mipnei shesofo letamei tuma chamura,
because in the end it can be a source of טומאה. tumah
How can this bird be a source of טומאה? tumah If you
swallow it. So since this bird can become a source of טומאה
tumah if you swallow it, even though here it's just sitting on
the table and you're just touching it, it doesn't require הכשר. hechsher.
Anything that in the end is going to be a source of
טומאה tumah. does not require הכשר hechsher to make it susceptible. It's
already enough under the, you know, ambit of טומאה tumah that therefore
it's susceptible even without liquid. So this meat, which when the animal
dies will be a נבלה, nevela, and now we're talking about those
few minutes when the animal's thrashing that it's not yet a נבלה
nevela but it's still food, why does it need liquid to make
it susceptible? So אמר חזקיה, amar Chizkiyah, said חזקיה, Chizkiyah, הואיל ויכול
לגררה ולהעמידה על פחות מכזית. ho'il veyachol legorerah uleha'amidah al pachot michezayit.
Oh, because you can make it so that it'll never be a
נבלה. nevela. How can you make it so it'll never be a
נבלה? nevela? So, a good thing Bobby isn't here, because here's the
scenario: you basically start dismembering the animal while it's still thrashing around.
Now, if it's still alive and you dismember, if you don't take
off a whole limb—if you take off a whole limb it's אבר
מן החי eiver min hachai which causes טומאה, tumah but if you
don't take off a whole limb, you dismember it and you cut
off partial limbs, then it's בשר מן החי. basar min hachai. It's
not a source of טומאה. tumah So if you total dismember it
while it's still thrashing around before it's died, then even after it
dies, those things that were taken off while it was still alive
will never be a נבלה. nevela. The only part that's a נבלה
nevela is the part that's still connected to the animal when the
animal dies. Now exactly how you manage to flay it so completely
that there is only a—less than a כזית of meat left on
it and it still hasn't died, I'm not exactly sure how you
do that, but anyway, at least in some hypothetical, this meat will
never have to be a נבלה nevela because you could tear it
off—the meat that let's say—at least the meat that you're touching, you
could tear it off while it's still alive and it will never
turn into a נבלה. nevela. Only the meat that's attached to the
animal when the animal dies will be a נבלה. nevela. What you
said—אבר מן החי eiver min hachai is
literally the limb, right, not meat.
Right, meat—בשר מן החי
basar
min
hachai is אסור באכילה asur ba'achila but it doesn't cause טומאה, tumah,
correct, yes.
So you used the word died, but I thought our definition of
death was שחיטה. shechita.
So that is a very good question which I am sort of
bracketing. Certainly our—when you שוחט shochet something, it's מותר mutar to eat
and it's not—not a נבלה. nevela. But for a non-Jew, it doesn't
go by שחיטה, shechita, it goes by death. Now the question is,
what does death mean? The neck is cut, right, and that's, you
know, the old brain death question. What do we mean? The heart
stops pumping. Exactly, it says עד שתמות, ad shetamut, but it never
actually defines what exactly that moment is. Okay, for our sake, we'll
say it stops thrashing around, there's no more any signs of life
in it. And you were saying for a Jew, שחיטה shechita death.
Well, I don't know if I'd say death. שחיטה shechita is—is—satisfies all
הלכה halacha requirements, all הלכה halacha issues. Whether we actually say שחיטה
shechita is death is a little bit unclear. Okay, that—we discussed a
lot of that when earlier in the פרק. perek. It remains unclear.
And this is a kosher animal. This is—or a Jew שוחט shochet
a non-kosher animal or a non-Jew שוחט shochet a kosher animal. Okay,
so basically the answer is, though, let's say the meat you're touching
won't necessarily be נבלה nevela because you could remove that meat before
the animal dies. And therefore, since it won't necessarily be a נבלה,
nevela, it requires הכשר. hechsher. So אמר ליה רבי ירמיה לרבי זירא,
amar leih Rebbe Yirmeyah leRebbe Zeira, said רבי ירמיה Rebbe Yirmeyah to
רבי זירא, Rebbe Zeira, ומי אמר חזקיה הכי, umi amar Chizkiyah hachi,
did חזקיה Chizkiyah actually—because חזקיה Chizkiyah was the one who just gave
this answer, so it shows that חזקיה Chizkiyah really believes, you know,
basically holds of our משנה about this idea that the meat has
this middle status. והא איתמר, veha itmar, we have a statement: שחט
בה שנים או רוב שנים ועדיין היא מפרכסת. shachat bah shnayim o
rov shnayim ve'adayin hi mefarchesset. So exactly this case, you שחט shachat
this animal, you did a kosher שחיטה shechita and it's still thrashing
around. But you did it for a—what do you call it? You
did it again, I believe in a—the scenario is, right, a non-kosher
animal for a non-Jew. So it's exactly the case of our משנה.
חזקיה אמר אינה לאיברים רבי יוחנן אמר ישנה לאיברים. Chizkiyah amar einah
la'eivarim Rebbe Yochanan amar yeshnah la'eivarim. Is it אבר מן החי eiver
min hachai for the non-Jew? So חזקיה Chizkiyah said it's not אבר
מן החי eiver min hachai for the non-Jew and רבי יוחנן Rebbe
Yochanan said it is. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan basically is what
our משנה says, that the שחיטה shechita is enough to consider it
to be food for טומאה tumah. purposes, but from the non-Jew's perspective
it's not, there's still another stage, it still has to die in
order for it to be considered to be kosher to eat, not
אבר מן החי. ever min hachai. But חזקיה Chizkiyah says it fully
works for the non-Jew. It stops it from being אבר מן החי
ever min hachai from the moment
you do a שחיטה. shechitah. So the שחיטה shechitah of a kosher
שחיטה shechitah done to a non-kosher animal is totally efficacious
even for a non-Jew. Stops it from
being an אבר מן החי. ever min
hachai. So if it stops it from being
אבר מן החי, ever min hachai, presumably that would mean one minute,
hold on a second. Right. So basically what that means, wait, wait,
wait, wait, wait. Oh,
okay, okay, now I got it. Now I'm sorry, I'm sorry. So
here's the point. The point is that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said
while it's still, the משנה said and presumably חזקיה Chizkiyah agreed that
while it's still thrashing around it is, it's not yet dead, right?
While it's still thrashing around it's not yet dead and it's not
yet, doesn't have yet the טומאה tumah of נבילה. But if חזקיה
Chizkiyah says from the moment you do a שחיטה shechitah on a
pig the non-Jew can eat from it, and if the non-Jew can
eat from it and it's not אבר מן החי, ever min hachai,
the גמרא gemara assumes, going to your point, that that means that
it's considered dead, right? Since from a non-Jew's perspective the point is,
is the animal alive or dead? If you're allowed to eat from
it after the שחיטה, shechitah, it means you consider it to be
dead. If you're considering it to be dead, then at this stage
it should cause the טומאה tumah of נבילה. So again, remember, in
this bizarre case a Jew's shechting a pig for a non-Jew. Our
משנה says at this stage it's not yet a נבילה, it's not
yet dead, so presumably a non-Jew can't eat from it yet, but
it's enough to be considered food. But חזקיה Chizkiyah says no, from
the moment, and therefore it doesn't cause טומאה tumah of נבילה yet
because it's not yet dead. חזקיה Chizkiyah says from the moment you
shecht it, it can be eaten by a non-Jew. Well, non-Jews, the
issue is alive or dead. So that means from the moment you
shecht it, it's dead. So that means he should be saying from
the moment you shecht it, it causes טומאה tumah. of נבילה. So
how does he work with our משנה? So let's take a look.
So the גמרא says, so רבי יוחנן אמר ישנה לאיברים, Rabbi Yochanan
amar yeshnah l'eivarim, חזקיה אמר אינה לאיברים, Chizkiyah amar einah l'eivarim, מיתיבי.
So here you go, just like you were assuming. If you can
eat it, it means we're considering it to be dead and therefore
it should cause טומאה. tumah רבי יוחנן אמר ישנה לאיברים, Rabbi Yochanan
amar yeshnah l'eivarim, no, it still is a problem of אבר מן
החי, ever min hachai, לאו מיתי, lav meisei, it's not yet dead,
even though you shechted this pig. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so
the answer is, יצתה מכלל חיה ולכלל מיתה לא באה. yatzta miklal
chaya u'l'khlal meisa lo basa.
No, there's a middle step, stage. It's no longer considered alive, but
it's not yet considered dead. Meaning just like for a Jew perhaps,
right, שחיטה shechitah makes something permissible to be eaten, but it's not
yet considered to be dead maybe, although there's very little הלכה halakhic
relevance. The same could be true for a non-Jew. Maybe a non-Jew,
it's an amazing idea, that a concept of שחיטה shechitah is relevant
for a non-Jew. Normally for a non-Jew we say the animal can't
be alive, it has to be dead. Here you're saying no, חזקיה
Chizkiyah could allow that שחיטה shechitah could work for a non-Jew and
they could eat from the limbs of it without yet calling the
animal dead. Okay, now the way I'm trying to frame it, it's
like שחיטה, shechitah, שחיטה's shechitah a מתיר matir even for a non-Jew.
Okay, that's not exactly what the גמרא says. The גמרא says it's
not אבר מן החי ever min hachai because it's no longer living.
But it's not yet the טומאה tumah. of נבילה because it's not
yet dead. It's in this middle state where it's neither living nor
dead. So the fact that it's not living means you can eat
the limbs, it's not אבר מן החי. ever min hachai. The fact
that it's not dead means it's not טומאה of נבילה. But one
way of understanding that is what חזקיה's Chizkiyah actually saying, that you
have a מתיר שחיטה matir shechitah which makes it permissible to be
eaten without it being considered dead.
Okay, so now the גמרא says, יצתה מכלל חיה
ולכלל מיתה לא באה.
yatzta miklal
chaya u'l'khlal meisa lo basa.
It's not yet dead.
What? Same would hold true for a Jew shechting a kosher animal?
A Jew shechting a kosher animal, the גמרא takes for granted, but
is, is, a, מותר mutar to eat, but for, you know, but
again,
is there a middle case for נבילה?
No, for a Jew of a kosher animal shechted, it'll never be
a נבילה even when it totally dies. So that's why you don't
have that interesting middle
state.
Can it cause טומאה before it fully dies? Or no?
Yes, it can for a Jew. Okay.
Any application of this to human life?
Well, that's always the question. The גמרא very sort of, it doesn't
make, very sort of, it's very sort of fluid in terms of
saying is it a מתיר, matir, is it considered dead, and never
is precise about defining death. You know, all the discussions about brain
death never really rigorously go through all of these גמרות Gemaras relating
to animals. I mean, some of them will quote, oh, it says
chopping off the head is counts like death, or you know, they'll
quote like one lines from it,
but the whole thing
together, like
30 years
ago, it was a whole thing about the process of death. Oh,
really? Uh-huh. That there's no point of death, there's a process. Right.
I never understood that, because I can understand there is a process,
but
there has to be...
Right. So that's always the question. I can accept that there's a
pro- oh,
there's no bright line is what you're saying.
But the problem is that I can accept that there's a gray
area and that there's a process, sort of like this, you're no
longer alive but you're not yet dead, and it would be- that's
interesting to talk about the possible הלכתית halakhic meaning of a middle
state of, you know, somewhere between the two. But you have to
at some point say there's like a בין השמשות bein hashmashos where
you don't know if they've crossed the line, but then there's a
point where it's לילה, layla, right?
So okay. All right. So anyway. All right.
Yes, so let's take a look. גופא. Gufa. שחט בה שנים או
רוב שנים ועדיין היא מפרכסת, Shachat bah shnayim o rov shnayim ve'adain
hi mefarkheset, חזקיה Chizkiya אמר אינה איברים. einah eivarim. So you שחט
shachted this non-כשר kosher animal. So חזקיה Chizkiya says it's not אבר
מן החי, eiver min hachai, a non-Jew can eat it, even though
as we said, it's not yet dead. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אומר
יש לה איברים. yesh lah eivarim. No, it's still אבר מן החי
eiver min hachai for a non-Jew even a כשר kosher שחיטה, shechita,
even if that makes it considered food for טומאה, it's still not
edible until it dies. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, נקוט להא
דרבי יוחנן בידך. nekot lehadra Rabbi Yochanan beyadcha. Take רבי יוחנן's Rabbi
Yochanan position, you should, you know, that's the right position that for
a non-Jew it goes by death, not by שחיטה. shechita. דתניא רבי
אושעיא כוותיה. Detanya Rabbi Oshaya kevataih. רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya taught like
him. דתניא רבי אושעיא, Detanya Rabbi Oshaya, ישראל ששחט בהמה טמאה לעובדי
כוכבים, Yisrael sheshachat behemah tmeiah l'ovdei kochavim, if a Jew שחט shachts
a non-כשר kosher animal to a non-Jew, שחט בה שנים או רוב
שנים ומפרכסת, shachat bah shnayim o rov shnayim umefarkheset, exactly our case,
כשר kosher שחיטה, shechita, it's still thrashing around, מטמא טומאת אוכלין, metamei
tumat ochlin, it can become טמא as foodstuff, that's our משנה, אבל
לא טומאת נבלה, aval lo tumat neveilah, not as a נבלה, neveilah,
so far everybody agrees to that, even ריש לקיש says it's not
yet dead, it doesn't cause טומאת נבלה. tumat neveilah. And now we
get to the question can a non-Jew eat it. אבר הפורש ממנה
כפורש מן החי. Eiver haporish mimena k'porish min hachai. If you rip
off a limb from it, it's like an אבר מן החי eiver
min hachai to a בן נח. ben Noach. It is not yet
permissible to be eaten by a בן נח, ben Noach, it has
the status of אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. ובשר הפורש ממנה
כבשר הפורש מן החי, Uvasar haporish mimena k'vasar haporish min hachai, which
is also forbidden for בן נח, ben Noach, it's flesh. The only
difference is whether it causes טומאה. ואסור לבני נח, Ve'asur livnei Noach,
and it's forbidden to בני נח, bnei Noach, ואפילו אחר שתצא נפשה,
ve'afilu achar shetetzei nafshah,
even after the animal dies, it doesn't matter. What defines its status
of אבר מן החי eiver min hachai is when was it removed
from the animal. So if you pull it from the animal when
it's thrashing around, it's still alive, it's אבר מן החי, eiver min
hachai, and even after the animal dies, it remains an אבר מן
החי. eiver min hachai. This was when it was a שחיטה shechita
on a non-כשר kosher animal. שחיטה Shechita on a כשר kosher animal,
totally permissible to be eaten at that stage. So you see it's
like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that it still is אבר מן החי.
eiver min hachai.
So it's even more severe for בני נח. bnei Noach.
Right, and that's really what חזקיה's Chizkiya logic, because חזקיה's Chizkiya logic
is how can there be something that is permissible to a בן
נח ben Noach that's forbidden to a- I mean the opposite, forbidden
to a בן נח ben Noach that's permissible to a Jew. But
since we're talking about a non-כשר kosher animal, this animal itself is
never permissible to a Jew, right? Because it's pork, not necessarily because
it's אבר מן החי. eiver min hachai. Okay.
Okay. שחט בה אחד או רוב אחד, Shachat bah echad o rov
echad, if he didn't do a כשר kosher שחיטה, shechita, then it's
meaningless. Then אינה מטמא טומאת אוכלין. einah metamei tumat ochlin. The only
reason it has a status of food is an act of שחיטה
shechita was done to it. But at this stage, it's not food,
it's not even an act of שחיטה. shechita. נחרה, Nachrah, let's say
you just sort of like, you know, נחרה nachrah is like, you
know, basically like you just shot it in the head, it was
basically by saying like you, you know, you kill it without even
trying to do a שחיטה, shechita, אין בה טומאה שכל כלום. ein
bah tumah shekol klum. There's no טומאה at that stage obviously until
it dies, and when it dies it's a נבלה. neveilah. So that's
another variation. The whole discussion of it having טומאה before dying or
being able to be considered food to receive טומאה before it dies
is only with a כשר kosher שחיטה. shechita. ועובד כוכבים ששחט בהמה
טהורה לישראל, Ve'oved kochavim sheshachat behemah tehorah l'Yisrael, and here's the reverse
case, a non-Jew שחט shechting a כשר kosher animal for a Jew.
So because it's כשר kosher and it's for a Jew and it's
an act of שחיטה, shechita, that's, you know, even though we're mixing
genres, it's a non-Jew, so eventually when it dies it'll be a
נבלה neveilah because a non-Jew שחט shechted it. But at least because
it has all the other positive things, at the middle stage it
still is considered food to receive טומאה. ומפרכסת, Umefarkheset, it's thrashing around,
it hasn't died yet. Same הלכה. halakha. מטמא טומאת אוכלין, Metamei tumat
ochlin, it can be the טומאה of foodstuff, אבל לא טומאת נבלה,
aval lo tumat neveilah, it's not a נבלה, neveilah, it hasn't died
yet. אבר הפורש ממנה כפורש מן החי, Eiver haporish mimena k'porish min
hachai, it's still considered alive, so therefore if you take a limb
from it, again, it's a שחיטה shechita of a non-Jew, so that's
why it doesn't count as a שחיטה, shechita, it's like אבר מן
החי, eiver min hachai, ובשר הפורש ממנה כבשר הפורש מן החי, uvasar
haporish mimena k'vasar haporish min hachai, ואסור לבני נח, ve'asur livnei Noach,
and the same with flesh, it's אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai,
בשר מן החי, basar min hachai, forbidden to a בן נח, ben
Noach, ואפילו אחר שתצא נפשה, ve'afilu achar shetetzei nafshah, even after it
dies, it remains אבר מן החי eiver min hachai because it was
taken from it while it was still alive. שחט בה אחד או
רוב אחד, Shachat bah echad o rov echad, if he didn't even
do a כשר kosher שחיטה, shechita, even though it's a non-Jew and
it's not כשר, kosher, that's seen as more of like a technicality.
But if the act is a different act, it isn't even cutting
both סימנים, simanim, it's only one סימן, siman, only the trachea or
the esophagus, right? It's pretty interesting, that's considered a bigger problem than
it being a non-Jew. Non-Jew the act was correct, the person who
did it technically it doesn't work. Okay, but if the act was
only one סימן, siman, then
about that's not
called שחיטה. shechita. Let's say a נכרי nochri started a שחיטה shechita
and he שחט shacht half of a סימן, siman, but it didn't
make it a טריפה. tereifah. If you שחט shacht half of the
trachea, the trachea only an animal is only a טריפה tereifah when
you שחט shacht the majority of the trachea. So he שחט shacht
part of the trachea, not the majority of it, and so he
didn't make it yet a טריפה. tereifah. ובא ישראל וגמרה uva yisrael
u-gemarah and then the Jew comes without pausing and finishes the trachea
and does the esophagus. So the non-Jew did part of the שחיטה,
shechita, but not a part yet that made it count and not
a part that made it a טריפה. tereifah. כשרה. ksherah. That שחיטה
shechita is כשרה, ksherah, even though he did part of the שחיטה
shechita since he didn't do enough to be an act of שחיטה
shechita and enough to make it a טריפה. tereifah. שחט ישראל, shachat
yisrael,
if the Jew started בין במקום שעושה טריפה בין במקום שאינו עושה
טריפה, bein bemakom she-oseh tereifah bein bemakom she-eino oseh tereifah, whether he
made it a טריפה tereifah or not, ובא עובד כוכבים וגמר uva
oved kochavim vegamar and the non-Jew ended, so the non-Jew is the
one who ultimately did the act of שחיטה, shechita, then obviously שחיטתו
פסולה shechitasto psulah invalid. Last line, this is like a whole fascinating
little big ברייתא braisa about like different scenarios of שחיטה. shechita. הרוצה
שיאכל מבהמה קודם שתצא נפשה. harotzeh she-yochal mibehemah kodem she-teitzei nafsha. You
want the meat from the animal that was sort of before the
animal died. Presumably that was considered healthy, although there's other גמראס gemaros
that say you're not supposed to do that, but it was considered
healthy because it had like a lot of blood in it. In
the process of dying, all the blood squirts out. You שחט shacht
it, it takes time for all the blood to squirt out. You
want to grab some of that meat before all the blood squirted
out because that was, for some people, that was considered healthy. So
what do you do?
חותך כזית בשר מבית שחיטתו, choseich kezayis basar mibeis shechitasto, you take
a grab grab a כזית of meat from the place you שחט
shacht because that's the most accessible place, right? You שחט shacht it,
it's open, the meat is there, grab a כזית of meat after
you שחט shacht it before the animal's died. ומולחו יפה יפה ומדיחו
יפה יפה, umolcho yafeh yafeh umadicho yafeh yafeh, of course you have
to do a good job of salting it and washing it out
because there's a lot of blood around there and in it because
the animal hasn't even squirted out all of its blood. וממתין לה
עד שתצא נפשה, umam-tin lah ad she-teitzei nafsha, don't eat it while
the animal is still alive because there's actually the גמרא in סנהדרין
Sanhedrin learns from a פסוק, although it's an אסמכתא, asmachta, that you're
not supposed to eat from even though it's כשר kosher as soon
as you שחט, shacht, you're supposed to wait till it dies. So
although we הלכתית halachically it is כשר kosher meat and you can
technically eat from it as soon as it's שחט, shacht, you're just
supposed to wait till it dies, it's not considered proper to eat
from it till it dies, ואוכלו, ve-ochlo, you can eat it. So
basically the point is if you want a piece of meat that
was really, filled with blood, grab it from the בית השחיטה beis
hashechita before the animal has totally died and then make sure you
do a good job of כשרing kashering it, wait till the animal
dies, then you eat it, but that'll be a piece of meat
that was really filled with blood out. Yeah, but presumably there's still
going to be more blood in it than will be in the
other meat.
And although it's a good point because if you're doing מליחה melichah
and we're we're going to cook it in a pot, then presumably
the מליחה melichah only works with the assumption that all the blood
comes out. So maybe it has to assume here that this type
of meat will retain blood that will never come out and therefore
you can, you can cook it after you've done מליחה melichah and
it'll still be better than other meat. אחד עובד כוכבים ואחד ישראל
מותרין בהם echad oved kochavim ve-echad yisrael mutarin bahem and this is
כשר kosher for a Jew or for a non-Jew this type of
meat that you grab from the moment of שחיטה shechita because this
is the reverse, right? A שחיטה shechita of a כשר kosher animal,
the same way a Jew can eat it while the animal's still
alive, a non-Jew can eat it as well. Got it? Meaning if
for a non-Jew שחטס shachts an animal, you שחט shacht a non-כשר
kosher animal, it's אבר מן החי eiver min hachai until the animal
dies. But if you שחט shacht a כשר kosher animal, the same
way a Jew technically can eat that meat while the animal is
still alive and thrashing because it was a שחיטה, shechita, so a
non-Jew can eat that meat as well. It's not אבר מן החי
eiver min hachai for a non-Jew.
Just read one more line I forgot we're not supposed to be
in this one today, so we'll have to end very soon. מסייע
ליה mesayei leih says the גמרא to רב אידי בר אבין, Rav
Idi bar Avin, this supports רב אידי בר אבין. Rav Idi bar
Avin. דאמר רב אידי בר אבין אמר רב יצחק בר אשין de-amar
Rav Idi bar Avin amar Rav Yitzchak bar Ashin הרוצה שיבריא, harotzeh
she-yavri, you want to be healthy, חותך כזית בשר מבית שחיטתו ומולחו
יפה יפה ומדיחו יפה יפה וממתין לו עד שתצא נפשה, choseich kezayis
basar mibeis shechitasto umolcho yafeh yafeh umadicho yafeh yafeh umamtin lo ad
she-teitzei nafsha, exactly this, grab a piece of meat from the place
you שחט, shacht, make sure you do a good job salting and
rinsing it, wait till the animal dies. אחד עובד כוכבים ואחד ישראל
מותרין בו echad oved kochavim ve-echad yisrael mutarin bo and it's מותר
mutar for a Jew and a non-Jew, it's not אבר מן החי
eiver min hachai for a non-Jew because it's not אבר מן החי
eiver min hachai for a Jew. בעא מיניה רבי אלעזר, ba'ei mineih
Rabbi Elazar, רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar asked, שהה בה דרס בה מהו.
shaha bah daras bah mahu. So we said there's a difference, a
non-Jew שחיטה shechita is meaningful to make it food, but שחיטה shechita
only one סימן siman is not an act of שחיטה. shechita. Let's
say you שחט shacht two סימנים simanim but you had a פסול,
psul, you waited too long, you put pressure, right, one of those
technical problems of שחיטה. shechita. Is that like you didn't do the
act of שחיטה shechita at all or like you did the act
of שחיטה shechita and it was a technical problem? And the נפקא
מינה nafka mina would be whether this thing would be considered food,
to become because is it like the שחיטה shechita of a non-Jew
so it's still considered food for טומאה. אמר ליה ההוא סבא amar
leih hahu saba an elder said, הכי אמר רבי יוחנן hachi amar
Rabbi Yochanan this is what רבי יוחנן said, צריכה הכשר
שחיטה tzrichah hechsher shechita כבהמה טהורה. kebehemah tehorah. So you need the
full שחיטה shechita like you would do on a כשר kosher בהמה.
behemah. And so therefore if it's not, if it has a technical
problem it does not have a status of making it like food.
הכשר למאי, hechsher lemai, so what do you mean to use that
phrase הכשר שחיטה, hechsher shechita, why not just say שחיטה? shechita? אמר
רב שמואל יצחק ודיקא סלקא. amar Rav Shmuel Yitzchak vedayka salka. So
the non-Jew who's שחט shechting your meat and is giving it the
status of food before it dies, everything else has to be perfect.
You can't pause, you can't put pressure, you even have to check
the knife before. Okay, so and the only thing
that we're exempting him from is having the right mindset or the
right כוונה. kavanah. But even if we say that, the fact that
you still need a perfectly fine שחיטה, shechita, there's another condition.